Hachette Audio presents Strange the Dreamer, written by Laini Taylor, read by Steve West.
For Alexandra, unique in the world.
Prologue.
On the second sabbat of twelfth moon, in the city of Wee, a girl fell from the sky.
Her skin was blue, her blood was red.
She broke over an iron gate, crimping it on impact.
And there she hung, impossibly arched, graceful as a temple dancer swooning on a lover's arm.
One slick finial anchored her in place.
Its point, protruding from her sternum, glittered like a brooch.
She fluttered briefly as her ghost shook loose, and torched ginger buds rained out of her
long hair.
Later, they would say these had been hummingbird hearts, and not blossoms at all.
They would say she hadn't shed blood, but wept it.
That she was lewd, tonguing her teeth at them, upside down and dying.
That she vomited a serpent that turned to smoke when it hit the ground.
They would say a flock of moths came, frantic, and tried to lift her away.
That was true.
Only that.
They hadn't a prayer, though.
The moths were no bigger than the startled mouths of children.
And even dozens together could only pluck at the strands of her darkening hair until
their wings sacked, sodden with her blood.
They were pearled away with the blossoms as a grit-choked gust came blasting down the
street.
The earth heaved underfoot.
The sky spun on its axis.
A queer brilliance lanced through billowing smoke, and the people of Weep had to squint
against it.
Blowing grit and hot light, and the stink of saltpeter, there'd been an explosion.
They might have died, all and easily.
But only this girl had, shaken from some pocket of the sky.
Her feet were bare, her mouth stained damson.
Her pockets were all full of plums.
She was young and lovely and surprised, and dead.
She was also blue.
Blue as opals, pale blue.
Blue as cornflowers or dragonfly wings, or a spring, not summer, sky.
Someone screamed.
The scream drew others.
The others screamed too.
Not because a girl was dead, but because the girl was blue.
And this meant something in the city of Weep.
Even after the sky stopped reeling, and the earth settled, and the last fumes spluttered
from the blast site and dispersed, the screams went on, feeding themselves from voice to
voice a virus of the air.
The blue girl's ghost gathered itself and perched, bereft, upon the spear-point tip
of the projecting finial, just an inch above her own still chest.
Gasping in shock, she tilted back her invisible head and gazed, mournfully, up.
The screams went on and on.
And across the city, atop a monolithic wedge of seamless, mirror-smooth metal, a statue
stirred, as though awakened by the tumult, and slowly lifted its great, horned head.